在本讲座中，我们将考虑单个机器人关节的速度如何影响
In this lecture we're going to consider how the velocity of a single robot joint affects
末端执行器的速度。这里有几个动画显示简单的双链接
the velocity of the end effector. Here a couple of animations that show a simple two-linked
平面机器人。在左侧，我们看到一个示例，其中机器人的关节1正弦变化。
planar robot. On the left we see an example where joint 1 of the robot is varying sinusoidally.
在右侧，我们看到一个示例，其中机器人的关节2正弦变化。但，
On the right we see an example where joint 2 of the robot is varying sinusoidally. But,
我们感兴趣的是各个关节的速度之间的关系
what we're interested in is the relationship between the velocities of the individual joints
Q1或Q2和末端执行器的速度。我们将能够即时显示出来
Q1 or Q2 and the velocity of the end effector. In what we will be able to show is that instantaneously
末端执行器的速度是末端执行器速度分量的总和
the velocity of the end effector is the sum of the end effector velocity components due
关节1的运动和关节的运动2。
to motion of joint 1 and the motion due to joint 2.
这是我们现在应该非常熟悉的双连杆机器人操纵器。我们展示了
Here's the two-linked robot manipulator which should be very familiar to us now. We showed
在之前关于正向运动学的讲座中，我们如何为x和x编写表达式
in the previous lecture about forward kinematics how we can write an expression for the x and
机器人末端执行器的y坐标。这是机器人的二维效应器姿势。
y coordinate for the robot end effector. That is the robot’s end effector pose in two dimensions.
现在，如果我们认为关节角度现在是时间的函数，那么我们就可以
Now if we consider that the joint angles are now are the function of time, then we can
计算x和y相对于时间的导数，这里的点符号表示
compute the derivative of x and y with respect to time and the dot notation here means the
关于时间的衍生物。所以xdot是x相对于时间的导数。
derivative with respect to time. So xdot is the derivative of x with respect to time.
Q1点是关节角度Q1相对于时间的导数。
Q1 dot is the derivative of the joint angle Q1 with respect to time.
计算衍生工具是相当直接的。这几乎是介绍性差异
Computing the derivative is fairly straight forward. It's pretty much introductory differential
微积分，我们需要应用链规则。让我们把前面的方程式带到a
calculus and we need to apply the chain rule. Let's bring the previous equations on to a
新页面。这里再次是xdot和ydot的表达式。
fresh page. And here again is the expressions for the xdot and ydot.
现在在这个表达式中你注意到有许多Q1dot和Qdot术语。什么
Now in this expressions you notice that there are a number of Q1dot and Qdot terms. What
我们能做的就是我们能把它们分解出来。这使我们能够以非常好的方式编写表达式
we can do is we can factor them out. And that enables us to write the expression in a very
紧凑的矩阵形式。如果您对此感到不舒服或者不理解我们是如何得到的
compact matrix form. If you uncomfortable with this or don't understand how we got from
矩阵形式的第一个表达式，乘以矩阵形式。乘以2x2矩阵
the first expression to the matrix form, multiply out the matrix form. Multiply the 2x2 matrix
通过2x1向量并说服自己，它与我们开始时的表达方式相同。
by 2x1 vector and convince yourself that it's the same expression that we started with.
我们现在可以用非常简洁的形式写出来。向量xdot和ydot是速度
We can now write this in a very succinct form. The vector xdot and ydot is the velocity of
机器人末端执行器。通常用符号J表示的矩阵被引用
the robot end effector. The matrix which is typically denoted by the symbol J is referred
作为雅可比矩阵注意，该雅可比矩阵是关节角度Q1的函数
to as a Jacobian matrix. Note that this Jacobian matrix is a function of the joint angles Q1
和Q2。所以我们这里有一个关节角速度，矢量Qdot，
and Q2. So what we have here is a linear relationship between the joint angle velocity, vector Qdot,
其中包括Q1dot和Q2dot以及笛卡尔空间xdot和ydot中的尖端速度。
which comprises Q1dot and Q2dot and the tip velocity in Cartesian space xdot and ydot.
我们刚才介绍的雅可比矩阵是以这位先生的名字命名的。一个19世纪
The Jacobian matrix that we just introduced is named after this gentleman. A 19th century
数学家CarlGustavJacobJacoby。他对功能表达非常熟悉
mathematician Carl Gustav Jacob Jacoby. He's been very familiar with a functional expression
像这样，y是x的函数，x是标量，y是标量。然后我们就可以写了
like this, y is a function of x, x is a scalar and y is a scalar. And then we could write
函数x相对于x的导数。它与y的导数相同
the derivative of the function x with respect to x. It's the same as the derivative of y
关于x。雅可比矩阵就是导数的矩阵等价物。它的
with respect to x. The Jacobian is simply the matrix equivalent of the derivative. It's
函数的导数，其参数是向量，其结果是向量。
the derivative of a function whose argument is a vector and whose result is a vector.
现在这些向量不必具有相同的长度。在这个例子中，x是一个向量
Now those vectors don't have to be the same length. In this example, x is a vector of
n维度和y是m维度的向量。
n dimensions and y is a vector of m dimensions.
所以我所说的雅可比矩阵是一个矩阵，在这种情况下它将是一个n乘m矩阵。
So the Jacobian as I said is a matrix and it will be in this case an n by m matrix.
矩阵的元素是每个输出的偏导数
The elements of the matrix are the partial derivatives of each of the outputs of the
关于函数的每个输入的函数。简而言之，这就是雅可比风格。
function with respect to each of the inputs to the function. In a nutshell that's what a Jacobian is.
当我们谈论运动学时，我们会介绍一种功能形式。
When we talked about kinematics, we introduce a functional form.
我们介绍了在机器人关节角度上运行的函数K并返回
We introduced the function K which operates on the robot joint angles and returns the
机器人姿势。现在我们正在考虑的双连杆机器人，关节角度属于
robot pose. Now for the two-link robot that we're considering now, the joint angles belong
到实数的二维空间和末端效应器的帖子也属于
to the two dimensional space of real numbers and the end effector post also belongs to
二维空间或实数。
the two dimensional space or real numbers.
关节角度向量Q属于二维实数的空间，它是
The joint angle vector Q belongs to the space of two dimensional real numbers, it's the
一组数字Q1和Q2。末端效应器的帖子属于二维空间
set of numbers Q1 and Q2. And the end effector post belongs to the two dimensional space
实数。这就是说末端效应器的帖子由两个实数表示
of real numbers. That saying that the end effector post is represented by two real numbers
x和y。我们刚才介绍的另一个符号是空间速度。和
x and y. The other symbol that we introduced a moment ago is the spatial velocity. And
我们使用希腊字母nu，它看起来像V和它的方便，因为它是一种类型
we used the Greek letter nu, it looks like a V and its handy because it is a type of
速度，但它不仅仅是平原上的速度。它还包括旋转速度，
velocity but it's not just a velocity in the plain. It also includes rotational velocity,
当我们谈论在三维空间上运行的机器人时，这变得非常重要。
That becomes really important when we talk about robots that operates on three dimensional space.